Guide to the Andrew Tallon Papers, approximately 1990-2016
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Andrew Tallon Papers
approximately 1990-2016
Tallon, Andrew, 1969-2018
12 boxes (4 cubic feet)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Syllabi, course outlines, notes, journals, collected offprints, and photocopies of academic manuscripts.
Biographical Note
Andrew J. Tallon (1969-2018) was educated at Princeton and Columbia Universities and joined the faculty at Vassar College in the Department of Art in 2007. Tallon taught medieval art, architecture, and pre-modern acoustics. He received a Ph.D. from Columbia University, M.A. from the University of Paris-Sorbonne, and B.A. with highest honors from Princeton University.
Tallon was an innovative scholar of French Gothic art and architecture, who introduced new digital techniques to the analysis and re-creation of the spatial archaeology of medieval buildings. His published works include The Structure of Gothic, and Notre-Dame de Paris, coauthored in French with Dany Sandron and published in 2013. Tallon completed a study of the Cathedral of Bourges and a five-year study which culminated in the web-based project Mapping Gothic France. Tallon was a former director of the International Center of Medieval Art and of AVISTA, and was co-founder and a director of the US-based charitable association the Friends of Notre Dame.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains syllabi, course outlines, notes, journals, drafts and offprints of scholary essays, and photocopies of academic articles documenting the career of Anddrew J. Tallon. The materials also include subject files from Tallon’s years as a student in the United States and France, and as a professor at Vassar College; and sound recordings that Tallon used during lectures.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Digital files created by Andrew Tallon and/or his student assistant(s) in the course of his work on French Gothic art and architecture. A listing of these files is not available at this time.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Basilica di San Pietro in Vaticano; Cathédrale Saint-Etienne de Bourges; Columbia University; Notre-Dame de Paris (Cathedral); Princeton University; Princeton University. Chapel; Sorbonne Université; Vassar College--Faculty
Subjects:
Architecture and archaeology; Architecture, Gothic--History; Art, Medieval--History; Cathedrals--Design and construction--History
VCL Categories
Art and Artists; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, May 2022.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Marie Tallon 26 July 2021 (M2021-015).
Series List
- Series I. Coursework, (Boxes 1-4, 10, 11)
  This series includes research and study material from Tallon’s work as an undergraduate and graduate student at Princeton and Columbia Universities. Of particular note are notebooks containing cathedral interior sketches, syllabi with notations, and email printouts. Also included are photocopies of academic papers, articles, abstracts and offprints, many of which contain Tallon’s highlights and marginalia.
- Series II. Teaching files, (Box 5)
  This series gathers course outlines, syllabi, and handwritten teaching notes.
- Series III. Subject files, (Boxes 5-8, 11)
  This series collects research and reference materials, some with Tallon's highlights and marginalia, on subjects including acoustics, iron architecture, and liturgical drama. Also included are notebooks with handwritten calculations and diagrams of cathedral coordinates.
- Series IV. Writings, (Boxes 8-9, 11)
  This series includes academic manuscripts resulting from research completed at Princeton, Sorbonne and Columbia Universities. Some manuscripts include edits, inscriptions, supporting research documentation, and notes.
- Series V. Audiovisual Materials, (Box 12)
  Audiovisual material includes (2) CDs containing digital image files from the exhibition opening of Mapping Gothic France at the Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center (2012) and 7 CD audio recordings of medieval choral music that Tallon used in his lectures.
Container List
- Series I. COURSEWORK
  - 18th Century Architectural Acoustics, Professor Middleton, Columbia University, undated (Folder 10.1-10.3)
  - 18th Century and 19th Century French Architecture, undated (Folder 10.4-10.5)
  - Architectural Acoustics, Harris, Cyril, Columbia University, 2001 (Folder 1.1)
  - Architecture in 18th century france, notebooks, 2001 (Folder 1.2)
  - The Architecture of Sir John Soane and the Picturesque, 2002 (Folder 1.3)
  - Art and Architecture of Constantinople, Prof. Holgerklein, Columbia University, 2000 (Folder 1.4)
  - Art Humanities: Masterpieces of Western Art, 2003 (Folder 1.5-1.7, 10.7)
  - Bergdoll, Barry, Art History, Archeology, 2001 (Folder 1.8)
  - Byzantium and the West, Columbia University, 2000-2001 (Folder 1.9-2.2)
  - Cluniac Liturgy Seminar, 2001 (Folder 2.3-2.6)
  - Collected syllabi, documentary film, art and technology, natural history, architectural theory, 2001 (Folder 2.7)
  - Elementary Latin, 2001 (Folder 2.8-2.9)
  - French Eighteenth Century Architectural Theory, 2001 (Folder 3.1-3.3, 11.1)
  - German for Reading Knowledge, 2002 (Folder 3.4-3.6)
  - Gothic Architecture, oral exam study notes, 2003 (Folder 3.7-3.8)
  - Greek Art and Architecture, Marconi, Clemente, Columbia University, 2000 (Folder 3.9-3.10)
  - Italian Renaissance, 2001 (Folder 4.1)
  - Medieval Historiography Seminar, 2002 (Folder 4.2)
  - Paris in the Medieval Age, notebook, 2002 (Folder 4.3)
  - Proseminar Methodologies of Art, Columbia University, undated (Folder 4.4-4.5)
  - Roman Art II, Professor Brilliant, includes Tallon paper, Living Space: The Cultivation of Prospect...", 2000 (Folder 4.6-4.8)
  - Romanesque Architecture, bibliographies, 2002 (Folder 4.9)
  - Seminar on the Skyscraper, Violet le Duc, Princeton University, 1990 (Folder 4.10)
- SERIES II. TEACHING FILES
  - Art Humanities: briefings, 2003 (Folder 5.1)
  - Art Humanities: Masterpieces of Western Art, 2003 (Folder 5.2)
  - Art, Music, Archeology, course outlines, 2004 (Folder 5.3-5.4)
  - Islam, Art and Architecture, 2001 (Folder 8.6-8.7)
  - Proposal, Stephen Murray, Department of Art and Archaeology, 1995-2002 (Folder 5.5)
- SERIES III. SUBJECT FILES
  - 19th century acoustics, approximately 1990-2002 (Folder 5.6)
  - Aachen, liturgy, undates (Folder 5.7-5.9)
  - Acoustics, approximately 1990-2002 (Folder 5.10-6.2)
  - Acoustic jars, vases, undated (Folder 6.3-6.7)
  - Architectural models, Basse Oeuvre, Beauvais Cathedral, undated (Folder 6.8)
  - Architecture and Liturgy, approximately 1990-2002 (Folder 10.6)
  - Aubert, Marcel, 2002 (Folder 10.8)
  - Beauvais Cathedral, 2003 (Folder 10.9)
  - Cluny Souvigny, undated (Folder 11.2-11.3)
  - Diary, notes, calculations, diagrams, 2012, 2016; (2 notebooks) (Folder 6.9)
  - French Eighteenth Century Iron Architecture, approximately 1990-2002 (Folder 7.1)
  - Iron fabrication, 1996 (Folder 7.2)
  - John Soane virtual reality, undated (Folder 7.3)
  - L'acoustique Cistercienne et l'Unite Sonore, Larcher, Hubert, undated (Folder 7.4)
  - Liturgical drama, undated (Folder 7.5-7.6)
  - Liturgy, approximately 1990-2002 (Folder 7.7-7.8)
  - Mapping Gothic France, website printout, Mellon Foundation, scholarly materials, 2010 (Folder 7.9)
  - Musicological Aspects of Architecture, undated (Folder 11.4-11.5)
  - Paleography, undated (Folder 7.10)
  - Perrault, Pattie, reference material, draft text, undated (Folder 7.11-7.13)
  - Pitcairn, Raymond, Bryn Athyn Church, photocopies, correspondence 1917-1919, undated (Folder 7.14)
  - Princeton University Chapel acoustics, undated (Folder 8.1)
  - St. Peter's, Rome, design and construction, undated (Folder 8.2)
- SERIES IV. WRITINGS
  - "Architecture et Sculpture, Gothiques," Press Universitaires de Rennes, 2012; (offprint) (Folder 8.3)
  - Art et Architecture a Étampes au Moyen Age, Les Cahiers, d'Etampes Histoire, 2010; (offprint) (Folder 8.4)
  - "Einhard, Notker and the Ninth Century, Frankish View of Byzantium, 2001 (Folder 8.5)
  - "The Liturgy of the Cluniac, Priory of St. Pierre de Souvigny,", 2002 (Folder 8.8)
  - "Medieval Architectural Acoustics,", 1992 (Folder 8.9)
  - "Medieval Architectural Acoustics: An Inquiry Into Some Aspects of the Relationship Between Ecclesiastical Music and Architecture in Medieval France," Sorbonne University,", 1992 (Folder 8.10, 11.6)
  - "My 'Post-Modern Yearning': The Integration of Architectural Acoustics in the Study of Gothic Space,", 2001 (Folder 8.11)
  - "The Origins of Organum: An Acoustical Approach,", 2000 (Folder 8.12)
  - "The Play of Daniel at Beauvais Cathedral," including research materials, 2002 (Folder 11.7)
  - "Pierre Patte and the Late Eighteenth Century Conception of Architectural Acoustics,", 2002 (Folder 8.13)
  - "The Portuguese Precedent for Pierre Patte's Street Section," Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians, research documentation, galleys, 2004 (Folder 9.1-9.6)
  - Smith Western Manuscript 16, research documentation, notes, 2001 (Folder 9.7)
  - "Structural Problems in the Conception and Construction of New St.Peter's in Rome," Princeton University, 1991 (Folder 9.8-9.9)
  - "The Tie Beam as Anti-Seismic Device in Early Islamic Mosque Architecture, 2001 (Folder 9.10)
  - "The Vaults of Il Gesu," including research documentation, Princeton University, 1990 (Folder 9.11)
- SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
  - Mapping Gothic France Event, Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center, 2012; (2 discs) (Box 12)
  - Musical recordings used for Tallon lectures, undated; (7 discs) (Box 12)